<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mustre of scismatyke bysshopes of Rome otherwyse naming them selues popes, moche necessarye to be redde of al the kynges true subiectes. Cum priuilegio.</title>
            <author>Swinnerton, Thomas, d. 1554.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1534</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840583</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840583</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 147:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mustre of scismatyke bysshopes of Rome otherwyse naming them selues popes, moche necessarye to be redde of al the kynges true subiectes. Cum priuilegio.</title>
                  <author>Swinnerton, Thomas, d. 1554.</author>
                  <author>Robertes, Johan, pseud.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by wynkyn de worde, for] Johan Byddell [otherwyse Salisbury,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1534]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Johan Robertes [i.e. Thomas Swinnerton].</note>
                  <note>Although leaf A1v describes contents as "First a prologue. .. After that a goodly hystory .. of pope Gregory the seuenth, written in the latyn tongue, by .. Beno, cardynall .. Last .. the lyfe of ye fourth Henry, emperour of Rome .." [also by Cardinal Benno], contents actually consist of prologue only.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; Byddell's name from title page; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The prologue of the translatour.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Papacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Charitas.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>IVSTICIA</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Fides.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>¶ A muſtre of ſciſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyke byſſhoppes of Rome / otherwyſe naming them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues popes / moche neceſſarye to be redde of al the kynges true ſubiectes.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>PRVDENCIA</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>SPES</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Obedientia</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>entia.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <p>IB</p>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Iohan Byddell.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:2"/>
Londini in aedibus Thome Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleri typis impreſſ. Cum priuilegio adimprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum. ANNO. M.D.XXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:5102:3"/>
            <head>¶Here foloweth the couten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of this booke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Irſt a prologue, whiche diſcribeth and ſetteth forthe the maners, faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons, and vſages of popes / ryght mete and conuenyent for the tyme that nowe is: wherein alſo the popes power is breuely declared / and whether the worde of god written be ſuffycient to our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon or not.</p>
            <p>¶After that a goodly hyſtory &amp; worthy to be redde of al men, of pope Gregory the ſeuenth / written in the latyne tonge, by a ryght holy and vertuous prelate of the churche called Beno, cardynall at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame tyme / &amp; newly tranſlated into englyſſhe.</p>
            <p>¶Laſt of al foloweth the lyfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth Henry, emperour of Rome &amp; of Amayne, newe turned alſo in to our mother tonge: whiche Henry was cruelly impriſoned and depoſed, by the meanes of the ſayde Gregyry.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5102:3"/>
            <head>The prologue of the tranſlatour. ¶ Iohan Robertes to the gentyll indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent reder ſendeth gretynge and well to fare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſyderyng oh well beloued reder, that ſo many noble au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours / as well of ſcience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable as of wytte moſt clere and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, haue in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſondry workes ſo lyuely and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly depaynted and ſet forthe, as a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng ymage before a mans eyen, the vſe, fruyte or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytees of hyſtories / ſo that nothyng more, as concernyng the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacyon of them can be well deſyred / I thought it therfore a thyng lytell requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte, as at this tyme agayne of any ſuche thyngꝭ to make declaracion. And though I had attempted ſo to do, yet I do not ſtande (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked be god) ſo hyghly in myne owne conceyte, but whan I had done the beſt I coulde, and ſought all the corners of my wytte / I thynke not the contrary, but there myght haue appered as great difference of eloquence &amp; beautye of ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon,
<pb facs="tcp:5102:4"/>
bytwyxt my encomye or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and theirs, as bytwyxt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clereneſſe of the ſonne and the leeſt ſterre in the fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament. Therfore the premyſſes pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, I haue determyned to leaue that, and to procede to my purpoſe &amp; ſhewe the cauſe of my labours. ¶ There is a fonde folyſſhe fantaſye ragynge in many mens heedes nowe a dayes (that wolde to god they were ſo wyſe as they be many in multytude that be troubled with it) and that is this. The pope ſaye they can not <note place="margin">That the pope can not erre the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenoeth to diſprou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> erre. Truthe it is that if he be in a fayre hyghway without any turnynges, and wel hedged on bothe ſydes, vpon his mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les backe, I thinke he can not moche erre excepte he wolde cauſe his mule to take the hedge. But that lyghtly he can not, for a mule (men ſay) may abyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpurre very well. This fantaſtycall blyndneſſe was neuer endued by any man of littera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by ſome pekyſſhe pedler or clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng colyer, it is ſo groſſe of it ſelfe. well, be it neuer ſo groſſe, yet was I ones groſſed therin my ſelfe: For colyers be not
<pb facs="tcp:5102:4"/>
groſſe alone. Than chaunſed to come to my hande the lyfe of Gregory y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth, otherwyſe named Hyldebrande (herafter folowyng) wherin whan I had redde a lytell way, as a man wolde ſay, one leafe and one ſyde in the latyne tonge, &amp; ſe the abhomynacion that there was written, I begon ſome thyng to be moued, &amp; bote the lyppe, ſcratched my heed, and wexed excedynge wery: yet forthe I went. But whan I came to thende, and remembred the deteſtacyon, execracion, and myſchefe that I had there met withall by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and agayne howe ſhamfully, myſerably, and pytouſly the poore ſymple ſoules of Chriſtes churche had ben ſeduced &amp; moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked / not onely my ſelfe and one or twayne mo, but hundredes, thouſandes / ye al the hole worlde with this peſtylent perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, that the pope can not erre / and dyd ſe before myne eyen the playne contrary, ſo clere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can not be denyed / me thought I was bounde in conſcience, no leſſe than vpon the ſaluacion of my ſoule, to declare vnto other the truthe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and
<pb facs="tcp:5102:5"/>
the darkneſſe out of the whiche, by the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng of this forſayd boke I was delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Of this conſcyence, zeale, &amp; occaſyon I toke vpon me to tranſlate this hyſtory mencyoned / whiche although it be not ſo exquiſytely done, nor with ſuche eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of englyſſhe as ſome man wolde loke for in an hyſtory / yet ſhall I deſyre all men, whoſe chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhall be to rede it, to admyt my good wyll &amp; endeuoyre. And bycauſe no man (in the worlde that nowe is) can meane, ſaye, or do any thynge ſo well or with ſo clere conſcience, but that the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned peſtyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tonges of falſe detractours ſhall peruerte it to the worſte: therfore I <note place="margin">The ꝓte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaryon of the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</note> proteſt here before god, or I procede any further, that I entende no derogacyon to holy churche, holy popes, holy byſſhops, holy fathers, holy doctours, holy man, holy woman, or any other holy thynge / but onely the diſcloſynge &amp; vtteraunce of them that be naught, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng wyll be taken as holy, &amp; wolde haue men byleue that what ſo euer they do is well, and that they can not erre / 
<pb facs="tcp:5102:5"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d wyll if a man ſaye the contrary call hym heretyke, and be redy to burne hym, for other defence they haue none. But truthe it is that a galde horſe wyll kycke wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he is rubbed vpon the gall: and no man wyll make a prouder bragge, ſouer than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtarke thefe / as Iudas ſaid whan our ſauyour Chriſt ſhewed his apoſtels, that one of them had betrayed hym: Not I good lorde quod he. Here coulde I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyte many goodly enſamples of them that wolde be eſtymed good, &amp; yet in very dede be ſtarke naught, were not for dyuers cauſes: but amonge ſo many let vs be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with one. In the tyme of kyng Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Cardynall Iohan.</note> the firſt, kyng of Englande, there came in to this realme a cardynall of Rome, whoſe name was Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: this cardynall made a greuous exclamacyon agaynſte preeſtes concubynes / and ſayde that it was a ſhamfull thynge &amp; abhomynable in the ſyght of god, a preeſt to ryſe from a ſtrompettes ſyde, to ſacre the holy body of Chryſt / whiche notwithſtandyng the ſame daye, after that he had ſonge maſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5102:6"/>
in the mornyng, was taken with an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot hym ſelfe at nyght, lyke a good eua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelycall father. This thyng was ſo op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ly knowen that it myght not be forſaken nor hyd. If any man be diſcontent with the productyon of this enſample, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall deſyre hym to holde me excuſed / fyrſte bycauſe I do it of no malyce, god to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde / ſecondaryly for that, that no man entendyng to diſcloſe the maners of them that be naught, &amp; yet wyll be otherwyſe taken, can do any other but ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe as he knoweth. And in ſo doyng he muſt nedes call a thefe, by this name thefe / a knaue, by this name knaue, and ſo forth / wherwith no good man ought to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. Nowe (leeſt we be to tedyous) it is mete we aproche to our mater.</p>
            <p>GRegory the ſeuenth, or Hyldebra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ergius the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of that name / before he was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted pope of Rome / was ſurnamed / os <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i in latyn / in englyſſhe / ſwines mouth hogges noſe / or pygges ſnowte / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye wyll. whiche Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius bycauſe he was a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ſo fou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le a name / &amp; vnmete for ſuche a dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytye (as he thought) dyd chaunge his name / &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hymſelfe Sergius. So that euer ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce all popes haue vſed the ſame / as ye ſe here in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie the. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. whoſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name before was Hylde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brande.</note> of whom we ſpake before, beſyde that that he was a damnable heretike of the ſecte of Arriane, as it is very euydent to be ſene in his lyfe / was alſo ſo cruell a tyraunt &amp; ſo leude of maners otherwyſe,
<pb facs="tcp:5102:6"/>
as neuer god put life in a worſe. And euen here without any more buſyneſſe (as an olde rotten houſe, blowen ouer with the wynde) cometh downe in a myſchefe our olde rotten raynebeaten opinyon, that the pope can not erre. For that ones admyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that he was an Arriane, as truthe is (if any crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is to be gyuen to a worldly ſtory) than no doute but he was an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke condempned by the moſte famous counſayle of Nece. If the popes warry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours wyll fyght agayne thyſtory, and ſay it is of none authorite and credence: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that they muſt approue it nedes, if they wyll at leeſt approue hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is euen next coſyne germayne to our holy father. For he that wrote the booke in the latyne tonge, was one Beno cardynall at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame tyme / whiche I ſuppoſe was a very good man, ye and coulde erre very lytell, if the pope can not erre at all. Neyther is it beſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauyng of this opinyon, that ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye the truthe of this ſtory, leeſt in your moſte nede other men ſerue you of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſauce, in the thynges wherin ye wolde
<pb facs="tcp:5102:7"/>
beſt be byleued, as in ſuche thyngꝭ wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ye haue nothyng to ſhewe but ſtories / and than ye be at a prety poynte.</p>
            <p>Peraduenture it wyll be anſwered, that lykewyſe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aperyng of one ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe proueth not the ſpringe of the yere, no more dothe the errour of one man, no not of four or fyue conclude that an other or all haue erred in dede. Mary that is truthe / who gothe aboute to proue that? Our argument is no more but vpon poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſybylite, as thus. Gregory y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth dyd erre and was an heretyke / ergo an other <note place="margin">Fyue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes ſtarke heretikes.</note> may ſo do. Or thus: Gregory the ſeuenth was an heretyke. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde was an heretyke. Liberius was an heretyke. Nouatus was an heretyke. Anaſtaſius the ſeconde was an heretike / and it is not vnpoſſyble but the reſt myght be herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: ergo all myght be heretykes. Ye, I dare be bolde to ſaye, that if men wolde make ſo fatte heretykes as be made now a dayes, they were no better all for the moſte parte. Some man wolde ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that myne argument is naught.
<pb facs="tcp:5102:7"/>
And than I ſaye agayne (ſauynge my charyte) he vnderſtandeth naught. For though there were no waye to fortyfye myne argument but the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men maner of ſpeakynge, yet coulde I do it. As for an enſample: whan men ſay a dagger is but dethe / it is as moche to ſay to al men that haue any wytte, as all daggers be dethe. And whan they ſaye: I wolde not truſte my father, if his hoode and his cote were ſowed togyder, or if he dyd weare a ſhorne crowne: ſome wyſe man wolde take it ſo, that none ſuche were to be truſted / and than me thynke they be but euen a ryght bare ſorte. Semblably (to choke them with their owne princyple) whan they ſay, the pope can not erre, their meanyng is that no pope can erre: and than muſte the contrary nedes be trewe, that whan men ſaye the pope maye erre, it ſigny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth ſo moche as all popes maye erre. And nowe I truſte to god our argument ſtandeth.</p>
            <p>Here haue ye proued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pope may erre, with the experyence of fyue proued
<pb facs="tcp:5102:8"/>
herctikes, condempned by the teſtymony of the churche &amp; good autentyke ſtories, whiche for the confutacion of this fonde princyple might ſuffyſe after my mynde. But bycauſe fyue make but a lytle ſhewe in a felde, let vs paſſe forthe and ſe if we can eſpye the hole armye of theſe blyſſed bretherne.</p>
            <p>For the more manyfeſt truthe wherof ye ſhall vnderſtande that from the yere of our lorde god. CC .xliij. vnto. M. CCCC .xxxiij. there hath ben .xxiij. ſciſmes in the <note place="margin">xxiii. ſciſmes in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</note> churche, amonge the popes them ſelues. Of the whiche the .xij. ſcyſme endured xvij. yeres. The .xxij. ſcyſme .xl. yeres, and the thre &amp; twenteth .xvi. yeres.</p>
            <p>¶ The .xxij. ſcyſme aforeſayde, was ſo darke &amp; doutfull, that the cronyclers can not tell (all the whyle it endured beynge the ſpace of .xl. yeres) who was the right pope / no nor the beſt lerned men and moſt of conſcyence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than were. And yet there was euer more choyce of popes ynough: for all that ſame tyme there were neuer leſſe than two or thre at ones. So that in
<pb facs="tcp:5102:8"/>
my conceyte if the pope can not erre, me thynkes one of them myght haue tryed the mater who was the true pope. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I doute but euery man ſayde for hym ſelfe, I am the trewe pope. But for as moche as none of them in ſo ſayeng were alowed of thother, it can not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery one iudged of an other, that he lyed and erred bothe / and was for the defendyng of his errour an antypope or ydole. yet the moſte wondre of all is, that it coulde not be diſcerned who was the trewe pope, by the beſt lerned &amp; moſte of good conſcyence that than were as the cronyclers ſaye. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this it foloweth that there was neuer a true of them all, or els y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the clergye or churche was very ſymple and coulde not diſcerne it / and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly had not Chriſt amongeſt them, to enſtruct them by his ſpiryte of all tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes: and than they were not the churche of god. For Chriſte hath promyſed to be with his churche to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of the worlde, to enfourme it in all vertue. Or if they lyke not that, than muſt they ſaye their
<pb facs="tcp:5102:9"/>
cronycles be falſe (wherwith hytherto they haue founde no faute) &amp; condempne them / and than we haue made a fayre brewynge. Conſyderynge than that the popes wolde not at thoſe dayes (whan they were two or thre at ones, ye and at other tymes whan they were fyue or .vj. at ones) alowe one an other / but iudged eche other to lye, erre, &amp; to be antypopes / what nede we any better proues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may erre, than their owne mouthes?</p>
            <p>In the tyme that theſe .xxiij. ſcyſmes endured, we fynde that there were to the nombre of halfe an hundred popes, ſtarke errant ſciſmatykes, anty popes, or ydols / whoſe names be theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Nouatus</cell>
                     <cell>Benedictus .x.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Liberius</cell>
                     <cell>Stephanus .vj.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eulalius</cell>
                     <cell>Benedictus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Laurentius</cell>
                     <cell>Hiſpanus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Syſinius <note place="margin">Seyſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes.</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Iohannes .x.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sergius</cell>
                     <cell>Petrꝰ de Carbari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſtoferus</cell>
                     <cell>Theodorus .ij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Damaſus .ij.</cell>
                     <cell>Iohannes .ix.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Formoſus</cell>
                     <cell>Alexander .ij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5102:9"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Benedictus .ix.</cell>
                     <cell>Romanus .j.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sylneſter .iij.</cell>
                     <cell>Benedictus .iiij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gregorius .vij.</cell>
                     <cell>Eugenius .iiij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iohannes .xxiij.</cell>
                     <cell>Leo .v.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iohannes .xij.</cell>
                     <cell>Chriſtoferus .iiij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Leo .xij.</cell>
                     <cell>Sergius .iij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Albertus</cell>
                     <cell>Innocentius .vij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Arnolfus</cell>
                     <cell>Gregorius .xij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Theodoricus</cell>
                     <cell>Alexander .v.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Petrus leonis</cell>
                     <cell>Gregorius y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyxte and two mo with hym / beſyde theſe foure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Alexander optayned of.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clemens .vij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus .vj.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bonifacius .ix.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Benedictus .xiij.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bonifacius .vj.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>GRegory the ſyxt aforeſayd was ſo <note place="margin">Gregorye the .vi.</note> rude and ſo vnlerned, that nedes he muſt choſe an other felowe to execute the offyce with hym, wherwith bycauſe many men were diſcontented, they electe the thyrde to put the matter out of ſtryfe / for the other twayne were fallen by the eares togyther.</p>
            <p>Nouatus the pope denyed that there <note place="margin">Nouatus.</note> was any forgyueneſſe of ſynnes to them
<pb facs="tcp:5102:10"/>
that had ones offended, but without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to be dampned for euer. If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can denye that this man erred, lette hym ſaye nowe, for this is the laſt tyme of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng. It were to longe to recyte all their errours / and therfore let vs ſe how ſome of this halfe hundred vſed them ſelues, as concernynge a parte of ſome of their lyues / for to reherce the hole ſtorye wolde aſke to longe a volume.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt to begyn withall, Bonyface the <note place="margin">Bonyface.</note> viij. a man of yll name and fame, by his falſhode and trecherye, diſceyued his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſour good Celeſtyne the fyfth, &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hym by a falſe pollecy to put him ſelfe downe. Bonyface perceyuyng that Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtyne was a very goddes creature, and eaſy to make a foole of, thought ſurely to ſhewe hym a poynte of ſopheſtry / and for the ſame purpoſe made as many frendes as he coulde. But amongeſt all, he had made a ſpecyall ſynguler good frende of one of the popes cubiculers / whom at the laſt he entyſed (for money) to take a great holowe rede / and therin to ſpeake theſe
<pb facs="tcp:5102:10"/>
wordes that folowe to the pope, in the deed tyme of the nyght. Nowe a man to ſpeake in a rede, maketh a very ſtraunge noyſe, as ye knowe. The wordes were theſe. Celeſtyne, yf thou wylt be ſaued, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounce the papacie &amp; pompe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, <note place="margin">Celeſtyne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> delude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ſerue me as thou dyddeſt before (the pope before ledde the lyfe of an anker) and this was done thre nyghtes togider. The good poore ſoule the pope ſuppoſyng this voyce to deſcende from heuen, dyd as the voyce co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym. But whan he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode the gyle, knowyng how falſly he was deluded, than he prophecied thus of Bonyface: as a foxe thou came vp, as a lyon thou ſhalt reygne, and as a dog thou ſhalt dye. Bonyface was of ſuche pryde &amp; arrogancye, that he was not abaſſhed to wryte hym ſelfe, the lorde of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, as well in tempora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tyes as in ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>altyes. And he inſtytute the pardone and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence <note place="margin">The Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the Iubilie.</p>
            <p>Benedict the .xij. was of ſuche diſdeyn and ſkornefulnes, that he thought ſkorne <note place="margin">Benedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of his owne kynrede / in ſo moche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan
<pb facs="tcp:5102:11"/>
any of them came to ſeke hym for ayde &amp; ſuccour, he anſwered that a pope had no kynrede at all.</p>
            <p>Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xij. was ſo hawte, proude, <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the xij.</note> &amp; gloryous in all that euer he dyd, &amp; ſo yll of lyuyng / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was iudged, not to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but rather to be damned / in ſo moche that good &amp; religyous fathers in theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout peticions &amp; prayers made vnto god, deſyred to knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate wherin he ſtode. Nowe yf he had made any good ende, or lyke to a chryſten man, what nede them put any doubte?</p>
            <p>Wherto ſholde I recyte the mooſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynable pryde that euer was herde of Celeſtyne the thyrde, whiche lyke an hore of the ſtewes paſt all ſhame, crowned the Emperour Henry the fyfth, holdynge the crowne bytwene his fete: and whan he had ſo put it on, he ſmote it with his fote agayne, nothynge aſhamed to ſaye, that he had power to make and depoſe Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roures at his pleaſure. whan notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng Chryſt ſayd that his kyngdome was not of this worlde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:11"/>
Calixtus the ſeconde, toke and impry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned <note place="margin">Calixt the ſeconde.</note> one Benedict a Spanyarde, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to the papacye by themperour / but fyrſt ſet hym vpon a mule, with his face towarde the tayle / &amp; cauſed hym to holde the tayle in his hande, in ſtede of a brydle / and to ryde through the cite with moche ſhame before hym. Some wryters ſaye, that it was vpon a camell / and in dede it is mooſt lyke to be trewe / to thentent he myght ſyt a lofte lyke an Emperour in a playe / and be ſene the better / to encreaſe his ſhame. Lo what charite is amonge theſe holy fathers? But yf he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hym to take the tayle in his mouth, and playe on it with his fyngers, in the ſtede of a bagge pype / than a man myght well haue prayſed the pagent, without any blame.</p>
            <p>I do warne the here good reder of one thyng / &amp; that is this. I haue left out here the names of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wryters, where I toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtaunce of this prologue, as touchyng what ſo euer thou ſhalt fynde therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the popes, &amp; Emperours, except
<pb facs="tcp:5102:12"/>
Gregorye the .vij. and themperour Henry the fourth / &amp; wyttyngly &amp; of this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, to proue wheder any man be ſo well ſene, to denye the leeſt iote or title vntrue, and that it can not be fortifyed by authors hytherto alowed.</p>
            <p>Of theſe .viij. popes that folowe / that is Bonyface the ſixth / Stephan the ſixth Romane the fyrſt / Theodore the ſeconde / Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .ix. Benedict the .iiij. Leo the .v. and Chriſtofer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt / I fynde no maner of goodneſſe / but that they be all togyder ſclaunderous, debatefull, &amp; myſcheuous, with ſuche contencyon as hathe not ben herde of at any tymé.</p>
            <p>And fyrſt of all Stephan, confermyng <note place="margin">Stephan the .vi.</note> thactes of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .viij. in that the ſayd Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> degraded Formoſus whan he was cardynal, to the ſtate of a lay man / &amp; enfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed hym to forſwere bothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cite &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeate: condempned alſo in his tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſus <note place="margin">Pope For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſus.</note> / with all thactes done of hym in the tyme of his papacye / and toke vp his body after it was buryed / and ſmote of one of his handes / and dyd the hande to
<pb facs="tcp:5102:12"/>
be caſt in the ryuer of Tyber / two of the fyngers fyrſt ſmytten of.</p>
            <p>Than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth Theodore the ſeconde / &amp; <note place="margin">Theodore the ſeconde.</note> he condemneth Stephan &amp; his actes / and approueth pope Formoſus &amp; his actes / &amp; ſo dyd Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .ix. in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel holden at Rauenna before .lxxiiij. byſſhops.</p>
            <p>Than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth Sergius / and daſſheth <note place="margin">Sergius.</note> all that was done of Theodore / and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth bothe Theodore / Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .ix. &amp; alſo Formoſus / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyng Formoſus body to be taken out of the graue ones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / and to be appareyled lyke a preeſt / and his heed to be ſmytten of in the ſeate apoſtolyque / and the body to be caſt in the ryuer of Tyber.</p>
            <p>Leo the fyfth was impriſoned of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtofer <note place="margin">Leo the fyfthe.</note> / and had the papacye withdrawen from hym by mayſtrye and violence: but Sergius the fourth thruſt out Chriſtofer and that ryght ſhortly / accordynge to the olde ꝓuerbe. Quade do / quade haue. Here is a turmoylyng I trowe.</p>
            <p>Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .x. was ſone to Sergius the <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tenthe.</note> fourth / bothe in fleſſhe and ſpirite / &amp; than
<pb facs="tcp:5102:13"/>
ye may be bolde he was no lytell honeſt <note place="margin">Marke the lyfe of theſe that fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low / by thende / for it is an olde prouerbe. If the ende be good / all is good.</note> man. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came by the papacye as moo of his felowes dyd / by vſurpacyon &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence / I wyll vſe no worſe termes / and at the laſt, accordyng to his lyfe dyed my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably in pryſon, his breth ſtopped with a quyſſhyon.</p>
            <p>Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xvij. came vp by ſymonye / <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the xvii.</note> by the helpe of Creſcentius conſull of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / and afterwardes (for no goodneſſe) had his eyes bored out of his heed / and the reſt of his membres al to cutte, hewed and mangled.</p>
            <p>Damaſus the ſecond entred the pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryche <note place="margin">Damaſus the ſecond</note> by power and violence / and by all poſſibilitie lyued well / for he dyed ſodeyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without howſell or ſhryfte.</p>
            <p>Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xxj. was not vnlerned / but <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the xxi.</note> a very foole in maners / and dyed as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhly. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a tyme (belyke whan the cuppes were full / for than be men mooſt wyſeſt) he prophecyed that he ſholde lyue many yeres / but it was not longe after, ere he dyed wretchedly, ſlayne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber fallynge on his necke, whiche was
<pb facs="tcp:5102:13"/>
but euen newe buylded. And here ye may ſe how true prophetes they ben.</p>
            <p>Wherto ſholde I recyte the greuouſe <note place="margin">Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the fourth.</note> and intollerable exactions, taſkes, &amp; pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, wherewith pope Innocent the fourth, bothe cruelly, wrongfully, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>charitably, pylled and vexed the Realme of Englande / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he was ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebuked of Groſtheed, byſſhop of Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne <note place="margin">Byſſhop Groſtheed.</note> at thoſe dayes, in a lettre ſente hym from the ſame Groſtheed / for the whiche lettre, and for bycauſe the byſſhop wolde not admyt a neuewe of the ſame Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, beynge but a boye, to a Canonrye than voyde in Lyncolne, he was accyted to Rome / and ther vpon accurſed / and the byſſhop appeled to the Throne of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie. After the byſſhop was deed, there appered to the pope in the nyght, one in a byſſhoppes rayment / and ſmote the pope vpon the lyfte ſyde, ſayinge. Aryſe vp wretche, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to thy dome. The pope was founde deed in the mornynge / &amp; his bedde all ſwymmyng with blode.</p>
            <p>Bonyface the .viij. of whome we ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke <note place="margin">Bonyface the. vii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:14"/>
before, dyed thus. As he withſtode the frenſſhe kynge / and enforced with all his myght and power to haue depoſed hym, Guyllyam de Longaret, a wyſe man and farre caſtynge / and other of Guyllyams frendes, made theym ſtronge / and toke pope Bonyface, whome after longe py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge in pryſon, they ſet vpon a wylde horſe, without any brydell, turnynge his face towarde the tayle / and makyng hym ronne, and prycke ſo aboute, tyll at the laſt he loſt his wynde / and ſo was ſiayne: but euen in a maner (as I ſayd) deed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with hunger / agreable vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye of Celeſtyne / as a foxe thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred / as a lyon thou ſhalte reygne / and as a dogge thou ſhalte dye.</p>
            <p>Iohan the .xij. by all lykely hode came <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the xi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of gentyll blode / for he loued well dogges and huntynge. And as for women, he kepte them but euen openly. At the laſt as he was takyng a lytell paſtyme with a mannes wyfe, for the recreacyon of his ſpirytes / the deuyll kylled hym ſodeynly, euen in the doynge of thacte.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:14"/>
Conſtantyne the ſeconde entred vngra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyouſly <note place="margin">Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne the ſeconde.</note> &amp; lyued vngraciouſly, to the great infamye and ſlaunder of all holy churche, and was at the laſt vngraciouſly ſerued / bothe his eyen put out, &amp; depoſed by the charyte (as writers ſay) of good chriſten people for his vngracyous lyfe.</p>
            <p>¶ I fynde it a trewe ſayeng, oh good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that who ſo regardeth his worke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygently hath lytell mynde of other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. In good faythe I was ſo beſy with theſe popes, that I had almoſt forgotten my ſelfe / and haue nye hande made halfe a worke in ſtede of a prologue: but I pray the of thy curteſye to pardon my forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and than I wyll ſpeake a worde or twayne of the depoſycion of the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Henry the fourth, with two or thre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo, and ſo make an ende.</p>
            <p>Fyrſte to remembre the moſte cruell, <note place="margin">Henry the fourth / Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</note> tyrannous, and pityfull handlyng of the excedynge good &amp; vertuous prince Henry the fourth, emperour of Rome and of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne, whoſe lyfe and hyſtorye I haue hereafter tranſlated: alas it wolde make
<pb facs="tcp:5102:15"/>
any mannes herte in the worlde to melte. Oh good lorde what man is that lyuyng, were he neuer ſo cruell or vnnaturall, whoſe eyen wolde not braſte out in we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge / to ſe ſo excellent a prince, ſo valy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt, and ſo vertuous to be ſo villay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly entreated, mocked, dryuen from place to place, caſt in priſon, depoſed, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed / and that euen of his naturall ſonne, lordes, and ſubiectes? The cauſe and doyng wherof was onely &amp; all togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Hyldebrande, otherwyſe named pope Gregorye the ſeuenth / as but to playne (if it pleaſed god otherwyſe) hereafter it ſhalbe ſene in both their lyues folowyng / and therfore I let it paſſe.</p>
            <p>Than go to Innocent the thyrde / and <note place="margin">Otho.</note> ſe how by the authorite of Quodcu<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaueris, he ſetteth vp &amp; putteth downe, and maketh hauoke. And fyrſte of all he enhaunſeth Otho the fourth, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hym Emperoure: but it was not longe or great varyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fell bytwene the pope and the emperoure. Than marke
<pb facs="tcp:5102:15"/>
howe that as ſone as Otho ones diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <note place="margin">Otho is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</note> Innoſent / by and by he is accurſed, and thervpon depoſed / and Frederyke the fourth is ſette vp in his ſtede. But not longe after cometh Innocent the fourth, and he depoſeth Frederyke / bycauſe he <note place="margin">Frederyke is depoſed.</note> began to withſtande the pope, and wolde haue taken no wronge at his handes as other had doone. This Frederyke was ſlayne of his owne ſonne / by whoſe enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragynge it is eaſy to coniecture.</p>
            <p>was not the emperoure Lewes the <note place="margin">Lewes the mylde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</note> mylde caſte in priſone alſo and depoſed of his owne ſonnes, by the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle of Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory the fourth?</p>
            <p>Dyd not pope zacharias at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt <note place="margin">Hylderyke depoſed.</note> of Pypyn, ruler of the frenche kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges houſe, depoſe Hylderyke the frenche kynge at thoſe dayes / and made hym a monke? It is a wonder they made hym not a monkas, or ſome other monſter.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe ye alſo but that kyng Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Kyng Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of England handled ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a warde.</note> of Englande was handled metely lyke a warde? whiche was fayne to yelde vp
<pb facs="tcp:5102:16"/>
his crowne to the pope, &amp; make ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full an othe of allegyaunce, to holde his crowne of hym / after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maner as I by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue verily no trewe herted ſubiecte may abyde to here of, moche leſſe than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte it. Ye, and what was the cauſe of the cruell handlynge of this good kynge? Forſothe none other but for that, that he right gentilly demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded a certayne ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of money of the whyte monkes, to ayde hym in his warres and nede agaynſt the yriſſhe men / whiche monkes anſwered ryght obſtynately (but clokynge their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynate pride with the colour of obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce towarde their religyon) that they durſte not ſo do, without the conſent and lycence of the generall and heed viſytour of their religyon, thabbot of Ciſteaux in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. The kyng notwithſtandyng whan he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourned from Irelande, compelled them as right was, for their proude &amp; diſdayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtubburnneſſe, to paye moche more than he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded before the ſettyng for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes of his voyage towarde Irela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</p>
            <p>An other cauſe was, for that that the
<pb facs="tcp:5102:16"/>
kynge wolde not admytte one Stephan Langton (a man of no ſmall pride &amp; fewe good vertues, as it apereth right well by the cronycles) to the archbyſſhoprike of Caunterbury, whome the priour and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent of the ſame had electe and choſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the kynges wyll, and ſent their election to the pope / whiche the pope con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed, and ſacred hym at a cytie called <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iterbi. If theſe be reaſonable cauſes (oh good chriſten reder) to enterdyte and accurſe this noble realme of Englande, the kyng and his counſayle, with all the dukes, erles, barons, lordes, &amp; other his ſubiectes that fauoured hym, I reporte me vnto the? If theſe be reaſonable and iuſt cauſes to pyll &amp; poll this moſte hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable realme of Englande euer ſens that yerely of a thouſande marke to be payde to the courte of Rome as a trybute, as the byſſhop of Rome pretendeth / with other incouenyentes expreſſed in the cronycle of Fabyane, the ſeuenth parte &amp; .xvj. leafe / <note place="margin">Rede Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byane and the crony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande.</note> and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cronycles of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the. lxxxiiij leafe and the .lxxxv. leafe, I reporte me to
<pb facs="tcp:5102:17"/>
the and to all the worlde. without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyon kynge Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was a good man, and a moſte vertuous kynge / but vngoodly handled and falſly dyffamed by a maly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyous ſorte of traytours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy after his dethe / and his lyfe and hyſtory ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully enterlaſed with moſt abhomynable lyes: wherfore I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntende it ſynguler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto thy goodneſſe to rede it with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecyon and iudgement. Here (good and fauourable reder) I appeale vnto thy ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſcyence, and adiure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in the behalfe of god, and as thou wylt anſwere / for as moche as thou ſeeſt here depaynted and ſet forthe before thyne eyen, the maners and faſſyons of the proude byſſhoppes of Rome (whiche be ſuche that it mere able to make any cleane &amp; chriſtened, and good englyſſhe herte in the worlde to abhorre at them) that thou from hence forthe be not ſo ſuperſtycious, ſo inſolent &amp; folyſſhe to thynke it well done, and alowed of god what ſo euer the rauenyng byſſhoppe of Rome ſhall do, without or beſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god. Ye, &amp; I adiure the alſo in the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:5102:17"/>
name and vertue that I dyd before, that thou ſuffre not thyſelfe to be led in blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; dampned in hell with them that helde with the byſſhop of Rome, than na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med pope Innocent the thyrde / agaynſt their liege lorde &amp; ſouerayne kyng Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou endeuoyre thy ſelfe to knowe thy dutye vnto thy ſouerayne and lyege lorde / and to reſorte vnto ſuche ſermons and bookes as ſhall teache the the ſame: vnto whom thou oweſt ſuche obedyence, as to ſhede thy herte bloode in his cauſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement / ye agaynſt an hole armye of byſſhops and popes of Rome, if the caſe ſhulde ſo requyre / as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne an armye of infydels and turkes. I meane where the byſſhoppe of Rome wyll take in hande to play the tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as he dyd with good kynge Iohan / there I ſaye thou art bounde vnder the payne of dampnacion to ſtryke. ye I affyrme bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that who ſo euer ones fauoured curſed Innocentes parte at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme, was damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for euer in hell / onleſſe he repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and were ſory therfore or he dyed. That pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:5102:18"/>
the electe veſſell of god ſaynt Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the .xiij. chapiter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> romaynes, ſayeng: who ſo euer reſyſteth the power (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temperall power onely) reſyſteth the ordynaunce of god. Nowe is it playne that who ſo euer reſyſteth the ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytteth dampnable ſynne / and ſhall receyue dampnacyon for his labour as ſaynt Paule ſaythe / oneleſſe he repent and be ſory therfore. And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aydours fautours, fauourers, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenters vnto ſynne be as well worthy of euerlaſtynge dampnacyon as the very doers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fact, is proued by thauthorite of ſaynt Paule, in the laſt ende of the fyrſt chapiter of the epyſtle to the romayns, by theſe wordes. The whiche (ſaythe ſaynt Paule, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the heathen gentyles in generall) all be it they knewe the lawe naturall of god, that all they whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte ſuche ſynnes / as be adnombred in the ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyter before) be worthy of dampnacyon / yet not onely they do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do them: as who ſhulde ſay, not onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doer but alſo the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenter
<pb facs="tcp:5102:18"/>
vnto ſynne, is worthy of euerlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacyon. Neyther can any man pretende ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before god / for it wyl not ſerue, as wytneſſeth Chryſt hym ſelfe in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell / ſaying. If the blynde lede the blynde <note place="margin">Math .xv.</note> bothe ſhall fall in the dyche. He ſayth not, that the one of them ſhall fall in the dyche but bothe. ¶ Wherfore ones agayne I warne, aduyſe, beſeche hertely, &amp; adiure all myne owne hertye &amp; welbeloued coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen of Englande, that they ꝑmyt not themſelues to be blynded with affection, with hypocryſye, or with ſuperſtycyon. Blyndnes wyll not helpe / &amp; therfore let it paſſe. Yf thou wylte knowe the byſſhops power of Rome / otherwyſe called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes power / as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyent &amp; ſyttynge that thou do / reſorte vnto the glaſſe of truthe, &amp; to the booke named the determinacions of the vniuerſities / where it is ryght ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly and paſſynge well declared &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated what the power of the pope is / how farre it extendeth / and what he may do. And to tell the my mynde ſhortly. Our metropolytane of Caunterburye, within
<pb facs="tcp:5102:19"/>
the realme of Englande, is a farre better man than he / both by thautorite of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the doctours of the churche, and the authorite of counſayles generall. And as for the byſſhop of Rome, otherwyſe called the pope that nowe is, all the worlde kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth well ynough what he is: a baſtarde a ſymonyake, an heretyke, &amp; a falſe vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of his dignyte. wherfore I can not meruayle to moche why my coutrey men of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, whiche had wont euer more to be cyrcumſpecte and haue wyſdome in all thyngꝭ, and fyerſe of corage to defende their kyng and realme manfully / ſhulde, ſeynge no cauſe why, but many and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent cauſes to the contrary / depende and leane to the vſurped authorite of ſuche a naughty and leude perſon. what ſayd I, authorite? ye tyrannye: whiche bycauſe our moſte gracyous and ſouerayne lyege lorde the kyng, wyll permytte and ſuffre hym no lenger haue his vſurped iuryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyction within this realme, and to carye awaye, exhauſte, and deuoure the golde, ſyluer, &amp; treaſure of his poore ſubiectes
<pb facs="tcp:5102:19"/>
and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mens, to moleſt and trouble them in his courte at Rome / &amp; dyuers wayes to oppreſſe and vſe his tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny ouer them by hym ſelfe and his, as he many yeres heretofore hath ben neglygently ſuffred to do. For this our cauſe (I ſay) it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he beareth ſo moche malyce vnto our moſte benygne protectour &amp; defendour our ſayd ſouereygne lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng, our vndouted ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitall heed vnder god / &amp; enforſeth therfore as moche as lyeth in his frowarde &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracyous pollicy and power, to bring his hyghneſſe and his realme to his vſurped obedyence / whiche moſte manfully lyke a moſt vyctorious &amp; chriſten kyng he dothe defende, not onely for hym ſelfe, but for the tender loue and pytie that he beareth to the weale of this his honorable realme and louyng ſubiectes, &amp; the delyueraunce of the ſame from ſeruage and thraldome. Here me thynkes I ſe euen the hertes of al true englyſſhmen leape in their bodyes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue that they beare vnto their moſt gracious liege lord, thus ſhamfully &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>elly handled for their ſakes, &amp; ſpeke vnto
<pb facs="tcp:5102:20"/>
them ſelues after this maner. Shall we ſuffre our kynges moſte gracyous hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thus malyciouſly, cruelly, and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to be entreated and ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and deluded of a baſtarde, of a ſymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyake, of a falſe vſurper, and of an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke / and all for the loue and fauour that he beareth vnto vs his poore ſubiectes / and for bycauſe his grace onely myndeth and tendreth our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite, weale, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte? No forſothe, we wyll not ſuffre his grace to receyue ſuch iniuryes &amp; wronges in any wyſe, ſo farforthe as it ſhall lye in our power to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary / but we wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayue like true &amp; louyng ſubiectes, whan ſo euer his noble grace ſhall ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs, ye but euen wynke vpon vs (to teſtify our true hertes &amp; myndes / that his moſte noble grace dothe not loue vs in vayne, and ſuffre ſo moch iniuryes for our ſakes onely for naught) drawe out our ſwordes lyke engliſſh men &amp; trewe ſubiectes / and manfully fyght in his graces quarell, to ſpende the beſt bloode in our hertꝭ to be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenged of ſuch a falſe bloodſupper &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:5102:20"/>
Let vs well remembre, note, and po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der what benefytes we haue receyued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges moſt gracyous highneſſe, by the ſpace of .xxv. yeres / &amp; what experye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we haue had of his procedynges, &amp; howe we haue ben defended from all outwarde enemyes, &amp; what glorious &amp; moſte victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious actes our ſayd ſouerayne hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid .xxv. yeres whyle he hath ben our king, &amp; in what welthe we haue lyued vnder hym / beſydes the thyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he now gothe aboute, as to defende vs from the theft, robbery, oppreſſyon and tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of the byſſhop of Rome, that moſte myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuous tyrant. Hath not his grace euer ben our protectour and defendoure, our ſhelde and buckler bothe in towne and in felde, agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theftes and robberyes of ſtronge theues &amp; murderers? who coulde paſſe out of his dores / ye who coulde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde at home in his owne houſe vnrob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed or ſlayne, were not for the feare of the ſworde wherwith his hyghneſſe moſte myghtyly hath euer defended vs? whoſe wyfe coulde be ſaued from ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſſhynge?
<pb facs="tcp:5102:21"/>
whoſe doughter and mayde from deflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſhyng? who ſhuld defende vs from the incurſyons of outwarde enemyes, as of alyens? who ſhulde ſe vs haue any right in the lawe? who ſhulde defende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore wydowe, the innocent, the fatherleſſe and the motherleſſe? Fynally if we had not a gracyous prince (as lauded be god, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme hath none ſuch) it were moche more pleaſure for vs to be out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde than to be in it, to be beeſtes that to be men / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderynge the myſery wherin we ſhulde lyue, if the ſayd byſſhop of Rome and his myght optayne that he and his moſte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre. The premyſſes therfore well conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, why ſhulde we not loue hym, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour hym, and defende hym with our ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and goodes to the vttermoſte of our powers / as our lyege lorde &amp; ſouerayne, as our protectour and defendour / ye as a very father vnto vs, as he is without queſtyon? And contrary, why ſhulde we in any wyſe loue, fauour, enclyne, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende any thynge to that tyrannouſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychriſt of Rome, whiche wolde with all
<pb facs="tcp:5102:21"/>
his herte ſe his grace, his realme, &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes alſo vtterly not onely ruyned, but alſo brought in perpetuall captyuyte and bondage / to thende that he with his cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes myght haue his dyuellyſſhe deſyre and luſte accomplyſſhed? and all this is for our ſakes onely. what profyte haue we by that foule romyſſhe ratten, but pyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng, pollyng, pykyng, robbyng, ſtealyng oppreſſyon, bloodſhedyng, &amp; tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny dayly exercyſed vpon vs by hym &amp; his? Dothe he not enforce to diſtroy and extynct vs as moche as lyeth hym? why ſhulde we be thus blynde? why ſhulde we be thus inſenſyble? Alas for pytie, let vs ones be wyſe &amp; ſerue god truly and our kyng / and god ſhall loue vs, fauour vs, defende vs, and be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs / &amp; than who ſhall be agaynſt vs? Remembre good reder what I haue ſayd I beſeche the hertyly in goddes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and as thou art a trewe ſubiecte / and away with Antychriſt of Rome.</p>
            <p>Here (moſte gentyll reder) all be it I inſtauntly requyred the a lytell before as thou woldeſt anſwer before god to reſorte
<pb facs="tcp:5102:22"/>
vnto ſuche bookes as maye perfytely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe the in the knowlege of the power of the romyſſhe popet or byſſhop, yet for bycauſe the mater is nowe in our hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge alſo / and for as moche as I deſyre nothynge more than that thou &amp; all other my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey men, may clerely ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> playne truthe, as conſernynge what his power is in dede / and by that to ſtycke &amp; abyde: I ſay &amp; boldly affyrme at fewe wordes, <note place="margin">The byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Romes power.</note> that the byſſhoppe of Rome hath no more authorite than hath any other byſſhop in chriſtendome gyuen hym by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture. To proue that, it ſhall be neceſſary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of Mathewe the .xvj. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all his hope and truſt is. But firſt thou ſhalte vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſauyour Chriſte putteth a certayne queſtyon vnto his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples, and demaundeth of them what the fame and reporte of the people was of hym, and howe they eſtymed hym &amp; toke hym in companye there as the apoſtels came / not for bycauſe that he was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt of the peoples talkynge: for howe can any thynge be vnknowen to god? but
<pb facs="tcp:5102:22"/>
to the ende &amp; purpoſe that he wolde after, that demaunde of them their owne fayth and byleue / &amp; haue it knowen to all men, as it was before knowen vnto hym ſelfe / to ſignyfye that his ſeruauntes, frendes, and louers whiche be taught inwardly by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyrit of his father, haue an hygher knowlege, vnderſtandyng, and a ſure by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and truſt / where as they that be not inſtructe in their ſoules by the ſame ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte, haue but a waueryng mynde &amp; opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon, ſhaken with euery wynde &amp; puffe of doctryne. The wordes of the ſcripture ben theſe. whome (ſayd Chriſte) do men talke that I am, that ſame ſonne of man? And they anſwered: Some ſay that thou art Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptyſt / other ſaye that thou art Helyas / other that thou art Ieremy, or one of the nombre of the prophetes. He ſayd vnto them. But what ſaye you that I am? Than Symon Petre anſweryng ſayd: Thou art Chriſt that ſame ſonne of the lyuynge god. Here thou muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de good reder, that lykewyſe as Chriſt proponed his queſtion not onely vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:5102:23"/>
but vnto all his apoſtels / euen ſo they all and not onely Peter, anſwered vnto Chriſtes queſtyon / all be it at the fyrſte ſyght a man wolde thynke the contrary by the wordes of the ſcrypture: but that anſwere of all them was made in Peter, and by Peter, in the name of them all / as in worldly beſyneſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreman of a queſt anſwereth and gyueth the verdyte for all his felowes. This affyrmeth ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne vpon this ſame place, by theſe wordes. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus reſpondit ꝓmultis: Oue <note place="margin">Auguſtyne.</note> anſwereth (ſaythe he) for many. Item the holy man Bede, our owne countrey <note place="margin">Bede.</note> man: Petrus reſpondit vnus pro omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Peter anſwereth (ſaythe he) one for all. Item Lyra: Peter (ſaythe Lyra) as <note place="margin">Lyra.</note> though he had ben principall of all, gaue anſwere for hym ſelfe and for the other. And the gloſe alſo called, Gloſa interlini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aris, ſaythe the ſame / and ſo dothe the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gloſe. And the noble clerke Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome <note place="margin">Chriſoſtom.</note> in his .lv. homely, vpon this ſame place of Mathewe / and vpon the laſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his .lxxxvij. homilie, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:5102:23"/>
Peter the mouthe of thapoſtels / for that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all they anſwered in hym, &amp; by his mouth, as by their forman &amp; ſpokeſman, as men call it. And that he was ſo it ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth well in the ſyxth chapyter of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where after a longe ſermon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt had made vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, wherwith they were ſo ſore offended y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they went murmuring away &amp; forſoke his audye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / he ſayd vnto all his apoſtels atones: wyll ye go alſo? Than anſwered Symon Peter. Syr, to whom ſhulde we go? Thou haſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordꝭ of eternall lyfe / and we byleue &amp; knowe that thou arte Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſonne of the lyuynge god. Marke here that he ſaythe not, I byleue and knowe / but we byleue and knowe, as beynge the mouthe and forman for them all. Of this it is many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt bothe by ſcypture and doctours, that Peter anſwered for all his felowes, and they all in hym / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his cofeſſyon was their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon. Forget not this good ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle reder, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte receyue no ſmall fruyte therby &amp; lyght, as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that I affirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſſhop of Rome to haue
<pb facs="tcp:5102:24"/>
no more authorite than an other byſſhop. For this ones grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted (as it can not iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be denyed, and as we haue ſuffyciently proued) that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels made anſwere vnto Chriſtes demaunde, and confeſſed hym to be the ſonne of the lyuynge god by the mouthe of Peter / than muſt it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des folowe of congruence, that what ſo euer anſwere and promeſſe for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon ſo made, ſemeth onely at the fyrſt lokynge to be yelded vnto Peter as retry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucion &amp; rewarde of his chriſtyan co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon / muſt of neceſſite alſo be yelded vnto the reſt of his felowes. For the cauſe (as ſayth ſaynt Auguſtyn) why Peter recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuche a promeſſe of Chriſt as he dyd, was his trewe and faythfull confeſſyon. Nowe the ſame cauſe of promeſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde beynge in them all, that was in Peter / why ſhulde they not all than enioy and optayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame gyfte, authorite, and promeſſe that Peter enioyed and optay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? ſpecially before ſo rightwyſe a iudge whiche had called them al to one offyce of apoſtleſhyp? Ye, that our reaſon is bothe
<pb facs="tcp:5102:24"/>
good and problable / and that all the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels had lyke &amp; egall promeſſe made vnto them all / ye euen the very ſame ſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter had made vnto hym, and all at one tyme &amp; place / we ſhall confyrme and ſtablyſſhe by thautorite of doctours, and reaſon corroborate by ſcripture. Our fyrſt doctour is the holy and worſhypfull man Bede, whiche confyrmeth our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd reaſon thus. Lykewyſe (ſayth this holy man) as the apoſtels generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of their byleue, Peter anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth one for all / euen ſo that anſwere that Chriſt made vnto Peter, he made to them al in Peter. This geare is playne ynough me thynketh. But let vs ſe what Lyra ſayth. And I ſay vnto the (ſayth Chriſt) that thou art Peter, and ſo forthe. where Lyra vpon theſe wordes of Chriſt: And I ſay vnto the (putteth to this gloſe) for the &amp; thy felowes. The ſame affyrmeth Ludolphus in his boke intytled, De vita Chriſti, euen by the ſame wordes: and ſo dothe the foreſayd gloſe interliniar or by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the lynes, ſayeng thus. Chriſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth
<pb facs="tcp:5102:25"/>
them all in Peter. And the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narye gloſe ſayth thus. The anſwere is made to one for all, to ſignyfye that vnitie ought to be obſerued amonge them all. Nowe this ones proued, as we ſe it is / and as it can not be denyed / but that what ſo euer promeſſe of power was here made vnto Peter, was equally and at one tyme and place made vnto all the reſt of thapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? How can the byſſhop of Rome, that vſurper, tyraunt, and bloode ſupper, for ſhame (yf he were not paſte all ſhame) ones mouthe it, that he ſholde haue any authoritie aboue an other byſſhop, conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering al thapoſtles had as moche power promyſed vnto them as had Peter, and all at one tyme, as I ſayd but euen now? Yea that there was no ſuperioritie amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſt the apoſtles, appereth in the .xv. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre of the actes of the apoſtles, where whan Peter by the waye of ſentence and iudgement, wolde haue rydde the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles, that were conuerted vnto Chryſte, from the bondage of Moyſes lawe, and from all the partes therof, Iames toke
<pb facs="tcp:5102:25"/>
vpon hym to correcte Peters ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and adiudged that for the weakeneſſe of the iewes, to thende that diſſencyon &amp; ſtryfe ſholde haue an ende bytwene the gentyles and them, adiudged (I ſaye) that that gentyles ſholde abſtayne from eatynge of meates off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vnto ydolles, from forny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon, ſtrangled, and bloode / ye and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned that ſo it ſholde be, ſayinge. My ſentence is (that is to ſaye, I iudge and ordeyne) that we trouble not them of the gentyles, whiche be conuerted to god &amp;c. And this ordynaunce ſtode, and was a playne correccyon to Peters ſentence / ſo that all men may ſe playnly, that Iames knowledged no ſuperiorite in Peter, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he muſt haue done, yf there had ben any in Peter. Yea yf there ſholde be any prymateſhyp or ſuperyorytye in any of Chryſtes diſcyples, me thynketh it ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be in Iudas and Silas, whiche in the ſame chapytre folowynge be called heed men or ſuperyours among the bretherne, whiche yet can not be vnderſtande, as
<pb facs="tcp:5102:26"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng any power that they had more than their felowes, but for ſome other ſyngler gyft wherin they paſſed the reſt. And yet in all ſcrypture is there no place that ſpeaketh ſo moche for Peter. That Peter alſo had no more authorite than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of thapoſtels is eaſy to ſe in the xviij. of Mathewe, where they receyued all as moche, as hygh, &amp; as great power as Peter had promyſed vnto hym in the ſayd .xvj. chapiter, al though the wordes myght be referred to Peter alone / as we haue iuſtly fortyfyed before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were not. The wordes of the .xviij. chapytre ben theſe. Trewly I ſay vnto you (ſayth Chriſt to his apoſtels) that what ſo euer ye ſhall bynde vpon erthe, ſhall be bounde in heuen / and what ſo euer ye ſhall loſe vpon erthe, ſhall be loſed in heuen. who ſeeth not here in theſe wordes as moche power conteyned as is in the .xvj. of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, where he ſayth. what ſo euer thou byndeſt vpon erthe, ſhall be bounde in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen / and what ſo euer thou loſeſt vpon erthe, ſhall be loſed in heuen. And yet in
<pb facs="tcp:5102:26"/>
this .xvj. chapitre of Mathew, the power is but onely promyſed. Wherevnto ſome of the papyſtes, obiecte well and wyſely, that goddes promeſſe is his dede and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, meanyng that as ſoone as the promeſſe was made, which is wryten in the .xvj. of Mathewe, it was performed euen by and by. I wyll make you a lyke argument. Chryſte was promyſed vnto Aoam, that he ſholde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me &amp; redeme hym and all his poſteritie from thraldom. ergo by theſe wyſe papyſtes reaſons, Chryſte was borne euen by and by. And it was promyſed in ſcripture, that a pure virgyn and mayde, ſholde be the ſauyour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. ergo yf god alwayes fulfyll his promeſſe immedyatly, Chryſt was conceyued and borne vpon our lady before ſhe was borne her ſelfe, thouſandes of yeres, long before the aungell ſaluted her, and went aboute inuyſybly to teche the papiſtes ſuche ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll argumentes. No doubte but our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes ben euer the beſt lerned, and beſt reaſoned men / where there be no mo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:27"/>
they. But let vs ymagyn that the power contayned in the .xvj. of Mathewe was promyſed than to Peter only / yet maketh it not for al that, that he had any ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte or primatſhyp ouer his felowes / in ſo moche as the contrary apereth in the xviij. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame euangelyſt, as it is before declared. Suche arguyng is moche lyke as though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges grace (god ſaue his hyghneſſe) hauynge twelue gentylmen ſtandynge before hym, and promyſynge one of them by name hereafter to make hym knyght of the Bathe, but appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge no certayne day / ſhulde happen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes, accordynge to his promeſſe, to doubbe hym knyght of the hathe / but with the other .xj. of his felowes, all at one ſeaſon and tyme. Nowe if this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylman thus by the kynges grace promo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, wolde take vpon hym to be lorde and mayſter ouer his felowes, bycauſe the diguyte was fyrſte promyſed vnto hym / I ſuppoſe verily y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reſt wolde thynke hygh ſcorne therof / and compte hym not very wyſe, nor yet take hym ſo in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e.
<pb facs="tcp:5102:27"/>
For all be it that the promſſe were made vnto hym fyrſt / yet they came vnto it as ſone as he / and had the ſame dignite &amp; as moche gyuen vnto them as had he / and all at one tyme. And ſo lykewyſe it fareth by the power &amp; keys ſuppoſed of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes to be promyſed vnto Peter onely, and before al other / although it be as true as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſee burneth. But admyt that it were of a truthe / yet dothe it not folowe immediatly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had any ſuperiorite ouer them / for as moche as euery one of them receyued the ſame ſelfe authoryte in the xviij. of Mathew / by theſe wordꝭ. Truly I ſay vnto you (ſaythe Chriſt) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what ſo euer ye ſhall bynde in erth ſhalbe bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in heuen / &amp; what ſo euer ye ſhal loſe in erthe ſhall be loſed in heuen. So that the moſte which they might proue if their ſuppoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion were true, as it is not / were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter receyued tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>orite of byndyng &amp; loſyng firſt, &amp; or any of thother receyued it: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che natwitſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng is vntrue. And agayn that there was no ſuperiorite among the apoſtels, doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy apoſtle Paule proue
<pb facs="tcp:5102:28"/>
the ſeconde chapytre to the Galathy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, where he ſaith thus. As ſone as Iames, Cephas, &amp; Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche ſemed to be the pyllers, perceyued the grace whiche was gyuen vnto me, they gaue vnto me &amp; Bar nabas theyr handes / and ſo forth. All the worlde may ſe by theſe wordes of Paule that Iames and Peter, whiche he calleth Cephas, and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were not in dede pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and heedes of the reſt of thapoſtles, but ſemed ſo to be, and that to ſome men / for the vehemencye &amp; diligence peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that they ſhewed aboue their felowes in ſettyng forth the worde of god. Marke here alſo how he ſayth not that onely Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſemed to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pyller alone, but Iames and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſemed to be pyllers as well as he, and were taken for as greate men as Peter was, whiche coude not haue ben, if his power had excelled theirs. Neyther dothe he ſaye, that Iames, Peter &amp; Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were of any power, or pyllers in dede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt / but onely that they ſemed to be the pyllers. Wherfore it is playne that they were not ſo, but contrarye, of egall
<pb facs="tcp:5102:28"/>
power and dignitie with the other .ix. Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> le here furthermore by the authoritie of Paule, that Iames and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were as hyghly eſtemed as Peter, but neuer man yet ſayd that Iames and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had any more authoritie, than Andrew, Mathew, Thomas, and the reſt, wherfore it conclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth that Peter had no more authoritie than all other of thapoſtles. And ſo it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that the pope hath no more autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie than an other byſſhop. Whiche grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, it argueth of neceſſitie, that he hathe no further to do, than within his owne dioceſe, whiche ought to extende no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to the next byſſhops dioceſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynyng to his. It argueth agayne, that he can reſerue no caſes from an other byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, that he can not ſende any i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terdiction in to another byſſhops dioceſe / that he can make no maryages / or gyue any diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacyons in another byſſhops dioceſe. &amp;c. Finally it argueth that he can do nothing in an other mannes dioceſe, for that that he hath not the worde of god to bere forth his acte, oneles the byſſhop of the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:5102:29"/>
for a more aduauntage, wyll conſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſurped power / and wynke ther at. Of this it is playne, that what ſo euer power the byſſhop of Rome hathe put in execucion within this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſynce the tyme that he fyrſt crepte in to it / is and hath ben nothynge els but ſtronge illuſyon, vſurpacyon, and tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ye / and euery peny that he hathe had, playne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torcyon, thefte and robberye. To this I adde, that all be it the wordes of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytye gyuen vnto all the apoſtles / and ſo conſequently vnto Peter, ſeme very large and to enclude alle maner of power in them, where Chryſte ſayd. What ſo euer <note place="margin">Mathewe xviii.</note> ye ſhall bynde in erthe / ſhall be bounde in heuen. &amp;c. Yet I ſaye that other places of ſcripture declare / that it ought to be vnderſtande of the ſpirytuall power one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of byndynge and loſynge of ſynne, by prechynge the worde of god, and myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrynge the ſacramentes. That the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd wordes include no power ouer tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraltyes, or temporall rule / is euydent by the .xviij. chapytre of Iohan, where
<pb facs="tcp:5102:29"/>
Chryſt ſayd vnto Pylate. My kyngdome is not of this worlde / which is as moche to ſaye to any wyſe man: As I am no worldly kynge, prynce, or ruler, nor haue any thynge to do in ſuche buſyneſſe, as concernynge my manhode, and the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſtracyon of my fathers worde. Here wolde I fayne lerne how the byſſhop of Rome came by his temporall power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe kynges and Emperours, ſeyng that Chryſte denyed ſuche power before good wytneſſe. I am ſure that the byſſhop of Rome hathe not more authorytye than Chryſt had. If Chryſt had no temporall kyngdom, rule, nor power in this worlde / than dare I be bolde to ſaye, that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of Rome hath none. And for as moche as there be but two maner of condycyons or ſtates in this worlde / that is to wyte / eyther the condicyon and ſtate of a kynge or of a ſubiecte / it muſt nedes folowe that the byſſhop of Rome, who wolde fayne be called pope, is, nor can be of any other ſtate and condicion than a ſubiecte / for as
<pb facs="tcp:5102:30"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>he as he can be of no hygher eſtate that was Chriſte / whiche knowledged hym ſelfe to be but a ſubiecte before Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, ſayeng. If my kyngdome were of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> .xviii.</note> this worlde (that is to ſaye, if I were a kynge in this worlde as I am but a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte) than wolde my mynyſters ſurely lyght, that I ſhulde not be delyuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iewes / but nowe is not my kyngdom from hence / as who ſhulde ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is trewe that I am but a ſubiecte, and therfore I may not fight &amp; reſyſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power and ordynaunce of god, but be obedyent thervnto as my father hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded. Ye &amp; to ſignify y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as concernyng his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode &amp; the admyniſtracion of his fathers worde, he &amp; his myniſters what name ſo euer they beare, muſt nedes be ſubiectes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges power / in the .xvij. of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew he payeth tribute for hym and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ye &amp; in Peter for all other thapoſtels and myniſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergye / whom Peter repreſented and fygured, to teche, declare and be an enſample to al that euer ſhulde ſuccede him and his apoſtels of their due
<pb facs="tcp:5102:30"/>
obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce towarde their princes. And this he dyd couertly, ſignifyeng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhulde come in the latter dayes ſuche falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and Antychriſtes as wolde teache the contrary, and withdrawe their dutye from their ſouereygnes. Here is it euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (oh good reder) that the byſſhoppe of Rome can be but a ſubiect, nor is: but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom? Forſoth to themperour. Than note my mynde in one thyng. Euery man knoweth that what ſo euer ſubiecte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth inſurrectyon agaynſt his liege lorde and ſouerayne, muſt nedes be a traytour vnto him &amp; to god alſo. The falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſſhop of Rome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nowe is, otherwyſe called the pope, hath done ye &amp; daily doth the ſame / ergo he is a traytour to god and thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: ye if thou enſerche thyſtories with good dylygence, thou ſhalte fynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there haue ben very fewe other this .vij. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeres. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſſhop of Rome be but the emperours ſubiecte / by what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte may he thinkeſt thou take vpon him to do that thyng that his owne liege lorde and ſouereygne themperour may not do,
<pb facs="tcp:5102:31"/>
at the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt by good authorite and iuſtyce, as to depoſe and ſette vp this kynge and that kynge at his pleaſure / whiche his lyege lorde and ſouereygne the emperour hym ſelfe can not do. And than he beyng but a ſubiecte, howe the dyuell cometh it to paſſe that he may do it? were it a mete thynge that the archbyſſhoppe of Yorke ſhulde depoſe themperour, or the kyng of Hungary? Nowe ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery byſſhop hath as moche authorite one as an other by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of god, as we haue proued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / why ſhulde not the archbyſſhop of yorke depoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng of Hungary or ſuche another man, as well as the byſhoppe of Rome that ſomtyme was, named Iuno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the thyrde, in a maner depoſed the moſte vertuous prince kynge Iohan of Englande / and brought hym to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremyte, that he muſt nedes to ſaue his lyfe &amp; crowne, and his realme from fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inconuenyentes, beyng a kyng knele downe before a knaue called Pandulph, the byſſhoppe of Romes legate, and yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp his crowne to the ſayde Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulphe,
<pb facs="tcp:5102:31"/>
as in to the handes of that foule monſtre and hoore of Babylone Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent beforeſayd / whiche crowne the ſayd Pandulph receyued and kept fyue dayes in his handes.</p>
            <p>My ſtomacke abhorreth to declare any further of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater, therfore I beſeche the what ſo euer thou art good reder, and the kynges trewe ſubiectes, to ſeke the reſt thy ſelfe. In my conſcyence if that ſame mater were well pondred and regarded with a trewe iudgement and a true ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes herte, of all them that maye and do rede it / with other moſte ſhamfull abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynacions that haue ben ſythe that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctyſed by that babylonycall ſtrompet of Rome and hers / as well in all partyes beyonde the ſees, as in our natyfe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and realme of Englande: I doubte not that if all trewe englyſſhmen knewe them perfytely, and pondred theym as they ſhulde do, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wolde, ye and therto myght with ryght good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyence deteſt, defye, beſpytte, and abhorre that ſame foule tode of Rome, as they wolde
<pb facs="tcp:5102:32"/>
and myght the graunde dyuell and capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of hell Lucifer prince of darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Nowe to make an ende of this mater, I haue proued that the byſſhop of Rome called pope by vſurpacyon, hath no more authorite than an other byſſhop, and that by ſcrypture, doctours, and the papyſtes owne gloſes. And that furthermore the power that he hath, with all other byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes is more ſpyrituall / and hym ſelfe but a ſubiecte with all his to the kynge and his lawes, bothe morall &amp; iudyciall. And that haue I dene by the authorite of Chriſtes own wordes vnto Pylate in the xviij. chapyter of Iohan, where Chriſte ſaith. Mykingdom is not of this worlde, as who ſhulde ſay / I am no kynge or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the worlde / and than muſt he nedes be a ſubiecte. Seyng than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt was but a ſubiecte in this worlde, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng his manhode / howe can it be auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded but the byſſhop of Rome muſt nedes be a ſubiecte? If he be but a ſubiect, how can he depoſe a ſtraunge and alyen kyng, as the frenche kyng or ſuche another the
<pb facs="tcp:5102:32"/>
whiche thyng to do his liege lorde and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereygne hath none authorite? Ye what maner of ſubiecte call ye that, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth his owne ſouereygne to kyſſe his fete, and wyll ſet the crowne vpon his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereygnes heed with his fete and daſſhe it of agayne whan he hath done / ye and depoſe hym therto whan ſo euer he lyſt? Howe agreeth this with ſaynte Paules doctryne in the .xiij. to the Romaynes, whiche ſayth thus. Let euery ſoule ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte hym ſelfe vnto the authorite of the hygher powers. By the hygher powers he vnderſtandeth onely the temperall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, as the proceſſe of the text manyfeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declareth / and excepteth neyther byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, byſſhop of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, nor byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Durham / neyther monkes of the charterhouſe, nor freres of Grenewyche / neyther father pye, nor father crowe / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther father gooſe, nor father gander / nor yet any ſuche lyke. But he ſaythe let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule ſubmyt hym ſelfe, or be ſubiecte vnto thautoryte of the hygher powers: where note that in ſayeng euery ſoule, he
<pb facs="tcp:5102:33"/>
except <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. And thoughe as I ſayde before he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>th hymſelfe afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the authorit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the kynge onely; ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e beareth not the ſworde for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aught yet the ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtle Peter ſetteth out Paules meanynge moche clerely i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his fyrſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> epyſtle and ſeconde chapytre, ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ytte your ſelues vnto all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ordynaunce of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an, for the lordes ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> / whether it be vnto the kynge as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the chefe he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d / eyther vnto rulers, as vnto them that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ente of hym, for the punyſſhment of y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> doers / but for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For ſo is the wyll of god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye, and marke what hyghe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ayſe is gyuen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kynge in ſcrypture. For he is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yniſter of god, ſayth ſaynt Paule in the .xiij. chapytre to the romay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And Salomon alſo in the viij. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre of his prouerbes / ſpeakynge in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſon of goddes wyſdome ſaythe thus: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e kynges do reygne. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not here howe Salomon extolleth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of a kynge / affyrmynge that realmes and kyngdomes be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gouerned, vpholden
<pb facs="tcp:5102:33"/>
and defended by the wyſdome of god? and that their power, offyces, lawes, and ordynaunces, ben the very diuyne power and ordynaunces of god? And in the ſeconde booke and twenteth chapyter of the Paralipo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, it is written thus of worldly princes and rulers. Ye do not exercyſe the iudgement and lawe of man / but of god. For as moche than as the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce and dignyte of kyngꝭ and ſuche heed rulers, ben ordeyned by the hyghe wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and prouydence of god / and for as moche alſo as his iudgement and lawe, is not onely mans lawe and iudgement, but euen the very iudgement and lawe of god / it foloweth very well accordyng to the ſayenge of ſaynt Paule: that who ſo euer reſyſteth the kynge and his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunce / <note place="margin">Paule ſayth who ſo euer / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cepteth no man.</note> reſyſteth the power, ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, lawe and iudgement of god / and ſhall therfore (accordyng to the mynde of the ſame ſaynte Paule) receyue eternall dampnacyon for his rewarde without amendement.</p>
            <p>Here (gentyll and indyfferent red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>)
<pb facs="tcp:5102:34"/>
euen as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntende not to collect and adde in this one lytell corner, all the places of ſcrypture whiche make, ſtablyſſhe, and confyrme the diuyne authorite &amp; power of kinges, ye rather of god hymſelfe / euen ſo my mynde was not vtterly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aue it all bare, naked, vntouched, &amp; blynde vnto the / but to ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome lyght knowlege and vnderſtandyng, in the obedyence due vnto thy prince / and gyue the occaſyon to enſerche and ſeke further for a more clerer perceyuaunce of the ſame. And thus I leaue ſpeakyng of the kynges power, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge a reaſon or twayne that we haue no nede of the byſſhoppe of Rome to be a generall heed of the churche of god / and that I proue thus. If we haue any nede of hym eyther we muſte haue nede vnto his lawes &amp; correctyon, whiche is falſe / for as moche as the kyng is bothe ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent and able with his counſayle to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe all maner of ſynne: or els we haue nede vnto his perſonall prechyng, whiche is falſe alſo &amp; can not be. Or els we haue nede to byleue as he byleueth, whiche is
<pb facs="tcp:5102:34"/>
falſe &amp; vntrue alſo / for than we had nede to be heretykes &amp; traytours / as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munly he is hym ſelfe. Or elles we haue nede of his myghty power / whiche is as true as that the mone hathe calued / whan hym ſelfe hathe no more power than hathe an other byſſhop / as we haue made clere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Now yf we nede hym i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none of theſe poyntes / than it is eaſye to coniecture &amp; to argue for a truthe, that he was neuer or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of god, to be generall &amp; heed vicare of the churche / but hathe purchaſed that authoritie onely by the ſwerde / and dothe falſly vſurpe it by tyrannye. For god and nature createth nothynge in vayne. One thyng I know, that he hath had moche of our money, wherof whether he had any nede or none, let euery man iudge. Yes ſay the papyſtes / it is mete that there be one that dare boldly tell Emperours, kynges and prynces theyr faultes / as who ſholde ſaye / that no man ſauynge the puppet of Rome durſt purely and ſyncerely preche, teche, and wryte the holy worde of god, wherein as in a mooſt true myrrour and
<pb facs="tcp:5102:35"/>
glaſſe, bothe kyngꝭ, Emperours, &amp; other, may beholde &amp; ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpottes of their ſoules. But your meanynge is (oh my fayre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes) that it is mete &amp; conuenyent, that there be ſuche a tyraunt &amp; deuyll, as may be able to lay a fayre ſwerde in the neckes of prynces, whiche they and theyr heyres and ſucceſſours ſhall neuer be able to reco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer, whan ſo euer they ſhall do any thyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to your appetites. But we taught by good experyence, are compelled to tell you agayne, that it is bothe neceſſarye and nedefull that there be none ſuche, and that we reporte vs to good kynge Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with other bothe kynges, Emperours, &amp; dukes, whome your almyghty god &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the puppet of Rome, hath full lyke a falſe traytour &amp; tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t depoſed. ¶ Here I leaue your lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puppet as I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de him for this ones, ſpekyng a worde or twayne of ſome of his clientes, whiche cleuyng to the clyfte of his lordſhyps clenſyng place, defende his godheed from the hygheſt to the loweſt, with the worde of god vnwry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten / ſo they call it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:35"/>
Truthe it is, that the worde of god vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wryten <note place="margin">Of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of god vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written.</note> is of as great ſtrength &amp; efficacite as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god wryten, I meane yf it be the very worde of god in dede. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore whan ſo euer any man wyll vſurpe vpon the (oh good reder) and fortyfye any mater, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name &amp; authorite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of god vnwryten, do no more but denye the vnwryten worde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he allegeth, to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god, &amp; put hym to the ꝓſes of it / and this be ſure of, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neither he, nor any of his ſhall euer be able to proue it. It may fortune he wyll enforce to proue it thus. There be many thyngꝭ neceſſary to be by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be not wryten in ſcripture / &amp; this is one of them. ergo this muſt be byleued of neceſſite. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maior or the firſt part I anſwere thus, that as concernyng the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſite <note place="margin">The fyrſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that the worde o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of god writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is ſuf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yent.</note> of our ſaluacyon, it is falſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there lacketh any thyng in ſcripture writen / for it is wryten Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. <hi>Sic enim deus dilexit mundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnigenitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daret, vt ois qui credit i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pereat, ſed habeat vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aeterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> God loued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde ſo intyerly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gaue his onely ſone, to thende that who ſo eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:36"/>
byleueth in hym, ſholde not peryſhe / but haue lyfe euerlaſtyng: and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre. <hi>Qui credit filio, habet vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aeternam.</hi> He that byleueth the ſone, hath lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng. And Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſixth. <hi>Qui confidit mihi, habet vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aeterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> He that truſteth in me, hath euerlaſtyng lyfe: &amp; ſo forth in .vj. hondreth places mo. Now ben all articles neceſſary to our byleue in Chryſt, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture wryten, &amp; they do ſaue vs, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proued (bycauſe that who ſo byleueth in Chryſt, byleueth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, &amp; ſo in the hole trinite) ergo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture writen dothe ſaue vs, &amp; is ſuffycyent to our ſaluacyon. And ſo is the maior / that is to wyte, that there be any thynges neceſſary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of our ſoules vnwryten in ſcripture, proued falſe. Mary otherwyſe to ſpeke of neceſſary thyngꝭ, truthe it is that there be many thynges neceſſary to be byleued of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gruence and good reaſon, that be not in ſcripture / as to byleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> falſe harlottes &amp; ſhrewes wyll neuer be true. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poules ſteple can not ryde .xl. myles vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a day, no though Lyncolne mynſtre were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:36"/>
The maior or fyrſt parte of their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aforſayd is proued vntrewe alſo, by thautorite of ſaint Auguſtyn: Ad fratres <note place="margin">Saynt Augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyn in the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke wryten to the chryſten bretherne / ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng in wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe.</note> in heremo, ſermone .xxviij. Satis enim nouit charitas veſtra, quod tota perfectio noſtre vite, et edificationis, ex euangelio accipitur. Your charyte (ſayth ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne) knoweth perfytly that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectyon of our lyfe &amp; edifycacion, is taken out of the goſpell. Nowe myne olde po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſſhe papyſtes, where is become your worde of god vnwriten neceſſary to be by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluacyon of our ſoules. Saynt Auguſtyne ſaythe that all the perfectyon of our lyfe and edifycacion, is taken out of the goſpell. If all be taken out of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, howe is any thynge vnwritten? Ye, and he ſayth not only all / but addeth ther vnto perfectyon &amp; edifycacion, whervpon it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your worde of god vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is of no perfection nor edificacion / and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is not neceſſary to be byleued to the ſaluacion of our ſoules. But pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ye wyll vſe your olde ſhamleſſe faſſyons, and ſaye that he includeth in this worde
<pb facs="tcp:5102:37"/>
goſpell, the goſpell of god vnwritten. Non ſic impij, noc ſic. Not ſo ye wicked, not ſo / for he expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth himſelfe of what goſpell he meaneth, in his .xxxviij. ſermon to the chriſten bretherne lyuing in wylderneſſe. Legite ſacram ſcripturam (inquit ille) in qua quid tenendum et quid fugiendum ſit, plene inuenietis. Rede ye holy ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſayth ſaynt Auguſtyne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ye ſhall fynde at full, what is to be helde and what to be auoyded. How ſay ye now, dothe not ſaynt Auguſtyne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs to rede holy ſcripture? but who can rede that that is not written / wherfore ye ſe that he ſpeketh of the worde of god writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten / and he addeth therto, that we ſhall fynde in it at full, that is to ſaye to euery wyſe man, ſuffyciently ynough what is to be holden, &amp; what to be auoyded. Howe lyke ye this worde at full, whiche before he called all the perfectyon and edifyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of our lyfe? And yet we fynde not in ſcripture your worde of god vnwritten. wherfore I conclude that it is not to be admytted and helde, for as moche as all
<pb facs="tcp:5102:37"/>
thynges that are to be holden, ben (as ſaynte Anguſtyne ſaythe) comprehended in the worde of god written at full. And a lytell after. Et quid tenendum, et quid vitandum eſt apertiſſime demonſtrauit. And it hath ſhewed vs (ſaith he, menyng of holy ſcripture) moſte clerely &amp; openly, what is to be helde, &amp; what to be refuſed. Howe ſay ye to theſe termes, moſt clerely &amp; openly? More ouer to come to holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture agayn / ſaynt Luke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt chap. of thactes, aproueth ſaint Auguſtynes wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des thus. Superiore quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> volumine dixi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus de omnibꝰ Theophlie, que cepit Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <note place="margin">The ſeconde argument.</note> tum facere, tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> docere. &amp;c. In our firſt volume or boke (ſaith Luke) we haue wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten of al thingꝭ o Theophilus, which Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus both practiſed &amp; taught. &amp;c. Howe ſay ye now to theua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt Luke, he excepteth nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt dyd or taught, wherof he hath not writen: wherfore if ye wyll be ſo good not to be diſcontent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt dyd and taught al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ neceſſary to our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / than muſt ye nedꝭ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Luke (though my new olde
<pb facs="tcp:5102:38"/>
mayſters haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wytte to eſpy them out) and than I put no doute but in the hole bodye of the ſcrypture written they be ſette forthe at full and at large / and ſo as for your worde of god vnwritten, ye may laye it vp to an other yere that there come ſome derthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. But what name ſhuld I haue better for theſe noble diuynes, than to call them doctours dreamers, or goſpellers ymagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natyfe <note place="margin">doctores ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginatiui.</note> /for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they proue is by dreames ymagynacions, &amp; ſcyence ymagynatyue.</p>
            <p>Paule the fyrſt chapiter to the romay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <note place="margin">The thyrbe argument.</note> ſaythe thus. Non enim me pudet euangelij Chriſti. Siquidem potentia eſt dei ad ſalutem omni credenti. I am not aſſhamed of the goſpell of Chriſt (ſaythe Paule) For it is the power of god to ſaue al that byleue, truſt, or ſtycke ſurely ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. I meruayle ſore howe our ymagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary fe doctours or goſpellers can auoyde me this place of Paule. Paule reputeth the goſpell of god to be of ſuche power and ſuffyciency, to ſaue all that byleue it: and than is the ſcrypture written ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent
<pb facs="tcp:5102:38"/>
to our ſaluacyon / and nothyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written pertaynyng to the ſame. Do we lacke any of the goſpell thynke you? than lacke we a pece of our ſaluacyon. Fynal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if our ymaginatyue euangelyſtes by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that we lacke any parte of it, for by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can not tell howe moche that parte is, nor how lytle, but be vncertayne therof / it foloweth that they be vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of their ſaluacyon / and wolde for that entent haue vs parte takers of their ſorowes: for it is a pleaſure to wretches to haue ſome companyons of their wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chydneſſe. Solatium eſt miſeris, ſotios habuiſſe malorum.</p>
            <p>Dyd not god alſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthe of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <note place="margin">The fourth. Non addeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad <abbr>vbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </abbr> / quod loquor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obis net auferetis ab eo. Deute. iui. ec .xvii.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the chyldren of Iſraell as foloweth? Thou ſhalt not adde any thyng to this worde, nor take any thynge from it. I beſeche you my wyſe vnwritten goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, for what entent was that / but bycauſe their worde written was ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient? Be we than in worſe caſe than they were / or dothe not this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de yet in effecte? Is it eyther iudiciall
<pb facs="tcp:5102:39"/>
lawe or ceremoniall / if it be neyther, than it apertayneth to vs as well as to them / and than go playe you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your vnnedefull vnwritten worde. Howe ſay ye now? hath not Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt chaptre of thapocalypſe? wyll ye neuer be wyſe.</p>
            <p>Anſwere to this: why dyd the apoſtels <note place="margin">The fyfth.</note> ſet their pennes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke to write? was it not bycauſe the goſpell of Chriſt ſhulde not be forgoten? And why than dyd they (as ye ſaye) leaue it vnſuffycient? Maye not the reſt that ye ſaye is vnwritten be forgotten? Yes: and is ſo moche forgotten all redy, that ye can not tell what it is, nor howe moche. By your tale a man myght well accuſe as well all as one of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels / bothe of vncharytableneſſe, as of wylfull neglygence and murdre of mens ſoules, in leauynge that vnwritten we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngly and for the nones, that is of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte requyſyte to the ſaluacion of our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / ſeyng it may be forgoten. And yet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary is knowen to well, that they were bothe to good, charytable, and dylygent / and loued the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:5102:39"/>
to well, to be taken tardye in any ſuche fautes / wherfore all your bablyng is not worthe a button.</p>
            <p>But what nede vs go aboute to proue <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the negatyfe, whan it is ſuffycyent for our parte, to denye there is any thyng ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to our ſaluacyon vnwritten in the ſcriptures: therfore (oh good reder which art not lerned) whan ſo euer thou haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuche reaſon made vnto the, demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of hym that reaſoneth with the, what he meaneth by that ſame worde, neceſſary. If he anſwere, neceſſary to ſaluacyon: denye thou that any ſuche thynges lacke in ſcrypture written. If he meane of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſaries, be not afrayde to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te it hym. As thoughe it be not written in ſcripture, that if our fantaſtycal doctours were vpon the ſpaynyſſhe ſees in a ſhyp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out bottome, they muſt nedes be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / yet muſt thou by neceſſyte of reaſon byleue it. Onleſſe their faythe were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than was Peters, whan he wente vpon the ſee / or that god wolde ſhewe a a hygher myracle than was done vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5102:40"/>
the holy mayde of Kent. And thus moche <note place="margin">The holy mayde of Kent.</note> for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futacyon of theyr maior. Now to the minor or ſecond parte of their reaſon.</p>
            <p>Whan they can not auowe the maior or fyrſt parte of theyr argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, than it is vnpoſſyble to make good the minor or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde parte / as whan it can not be ꝓued, that there is any thyng vnwryten in ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, neceſſary to our ſaluacyon / how is it poſſyble than to aſſygne or appoynt any certayne thynge, (as the faſtynge of lent, or any other thynge) and ſaye this is one of them? for I muſt fyrſt proue that there be ſome ſuche thynges vnwryten, ere I can ſay, this or that is one of them. As in example. Yf a man wolde ꝓue that there be ſome good and honeſt vnwriten goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, &amp; coude not make it good, yf he were put to his probacyon / how the deuyl than were it poſſyble for hym, to aſſygne and poynt out ſome certayn man of that ſecte, and ſaye, ſuche a man is one of thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and good men? And by my truthe I thynke it were as great mayſtry to proue that there be any good &amp; vertuous people
<pb facs="tcp:5102:40"/>
of that ſecte, as to proue that Chryſt was borne before our lady, I take no mo to be of that ſecte, but ſuche as defende this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronyous opynyon in the pulpet, or by wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge, or obſtynate diſputacyon.</p>
            <p>Now whan neyther the maior nor the minor can be ꝓued, where ſhall we fynde the concluſyon? God knoweth, for I can not tell.</p>
            <p>Yet to proue what our ymagynatyfe doctours can do, let vs for good company graunte that there be ſome thynges vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wryten neceſſary to the ſaluacyon of our ſoules / ſhall it folowe therfore, that thoſe ſame vnwryten verytyes, whiche ſome of them aſſigne to be the worde of god vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wryten, be ſo in dede? I wonder in what fygure this ſame argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Bocardo, or in Newe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate. Suche maner of arguynge is moche lyke, as yf one of theſe vnwryten prophetes, goynge to the feldes to ſhote, and lackynge bothe braſer and ſhotynge gloue, wolde proue that he neded his wyues nyght cap, and argue thus. By god I haue nede of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:5102:41"/>
thynges whiche I haue not, if I ſhulde ſhoote well. Mary that is truthe myght an other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> company ſay. Nowe if this wyſe man wolde conclude vpon the others graunt, and ſay / ergo it is my wyues nyghtcappe / myght not an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracyous felowe ſtandynge by ſaye / ergo it is an halter / or ergo thou wylte neuer be wyſe? yes in good faythe: excepte he wolde make a braſer or a ſhotynge gloue of his wyues nyghtcappe. Semblably whan our doctours ſaye: there be many thynges vnwritten in ſcrypture neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to our ſaluacyon to be byleued. ergo this or that is one of them / yet that ſame this or that foloweth not of neceſſyte, no more than the good wyues nyghtcappe dothe / ſo that if thou ſe cauſe why thou maye as well ſaye / ergo it is the good wyues nyghtcappe, or denye it, and put hym to the probacyon of it: and of this I dare make the warrantyſe, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he nor all the frendes he hath ſhall euer be able to make it good.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5102:41"/>
But the beſt ſporte of all is, that our vnwritten eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelyſtes be driuen by their owne confeſſyon, to forſake the worde of god written, as the thynge that is not able to beare them out in their trouble, &amp; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to ſeke this ſorye ſhyfte of the worde of god vnwritten, and that of neceſſyte as they ſaye. Of what neceſſyte euery man knoweth. Trewly bycauſe they be not able to proue the byſſhoppe of Romes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and tyrannye, with other erronyous artycles, by ſcrypture written / but grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t well and wyſely that the worde of god ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not on their parte, and muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make their refuge to the worde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſyble that flyeth aboute in the ayre, and no man can tell what it is nor where to fynde it. Be not theſe ſore felowes to fyght in a mannes quarell, that caſtyng their beſt weapons from theym, ronne home to their wyues &amp; ſay they be driuen to flye for faute of weapon / and deſyre a podynge in the ſtede of a ſworde? God ſende euery good man in a iuſt cauſe, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more wyſer cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle than he were
<pb facs="tcp:5102:42"/>
lyke to haue of ſuche men, whiche euen at the fyrſte choppe / ye and without any ſtudy to, confeſſe they be but beggers and haue no ware to fell. Is not a mannes money well beſtowed vpon ſuche mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes as crye creke euen at the. fyrſts brunte? Theſe be they that wyll beat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> downe all the worlde with then gonne ſhotte. But if other men had ben driuen to ſuche ſhamefull ſhyftes by them good lorde what exclamacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wolde they haue made. And as for the perpetuall virgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of our lady / no man douteth of it that I knowe. But in the meane tyme I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre my mayſters the papyſtes, with the proctours of bycherly buggerſters to tell me as they wyll abyde by, whether they byleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perpetuall virgynne of our lady to be comprehended in ſcrypture written or no? all be it I knowe that in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they haue ſayd naye all redy. But as for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wyll take no holde of it but gyue them for this ones the priuylege of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſhmen, that is to tell their tales twyſe, for at the fyrſt tellyng it may fortune they
<pb facs="tcp:5102:42"/>
were not well aduiſed, or ꝑaduenture the mens wyttes were rauyſſhed, or (as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune ſaying is) breched. Neyther is it good maner to take a man at the worſte.</p>
            <p>An other cauellacyon haue they, &amp; that <note place="margin">This cauela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion toke the patriarche of vnthriftes out of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karde.</note> is this. How knowe ye ſay they which is the true worde of god? Whervnto I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that as concernyng our outwarde knowlege, thapoſtles &amp; ꝓphetes haue left their myndes therof behynde them in wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng, by the whiche we may diſcerne the true worde of god fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dreames &amp; fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes. Well ſay they agayn. But how be ye ſure that thapoſtles &amp; ꝓphetes dyd write that ſame worde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? as who ſholde ſay, it is poſſyble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may be deceyued, &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byble whiche ye haue &amp; loke vpon, may be falſly intytled, &amp; be none of thapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles &amp; prophetes doynges. Whervnto I make anſwere, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as concernyng the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde knowlege, we haue as moche and good aſſurau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſelfe ſame worde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chryſt, his apoſtles, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓphetes taught: as that ſame ſorte, which ye cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, the preeſtes, monkes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eres, chano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, abbots, byſſhops. &amp;c. and
<pb facs="tcp:5102:43"/>
haue herde Chryſt, thapoſtles, &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes teche &amp; preche as often as euer did they / &amp; ſene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as often as euer dyd they. Wherfore as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outwarde tytle &amp; knowlege, as I ſaid before, we be ſo wel aſſured therof as they ben, and receyue no knowlege of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they receyue of vs. Neither haue they any better know lege in this behalfe, than we haue. Than procede our wyſe dreamyng doctours fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / &amp; affirme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poraltie haue none other knowlege &amp; aſſurau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worde of god, but bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the clergye as they meane, beyng aſſured which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worde, &amp; which not, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtruction &amp; techyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, doth certifie &amp; tell vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſpirit, which is that ſame true worde of god. It is an olde ſayd ſawe (good reder) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſhal ſoone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceyue a thefe by his own tale. Theſe olde bottell bretherne be ſo ſubtyl, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wote not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde what they ſay. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>myſe you they ben excedyng connyng in wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armes / but whan they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to the collers, they ben choked vp forthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, as the deuyl wolde / &amp; caſt in theyr owne trip.
<pb facs="tcp:5102:43"/>
Let vs marke well their wordes, and ſe what they haue won by their owne tale and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt (as they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and as there is no doute) euſtructeth the churche &amp; teacheth her to diſcerne the true worde of god, from falſe dremes and fantaſyes / than is it as falſe as euer god almyghty was true or is, that we of the temperaltye haue no other knowlege or aſſurau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whiche is the trewe worde of god, but by the ſpirytualty, for as moche as we by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> redemptyon that is in Chriſt Ieſu be of the ſame churche, that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe, taught, &amp; made perfyte in all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytees or truthes. For loke howe the holy ghoſt enfourmeth &amp; teacheth all the hole holy catholyke churche of god / euen ſo he inſpyreth &amp; teacheth euery trewe and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng membre of the ſame, in all veritees and truthes neceſſary to their ſaluacyon. But truthe it is that the papyſticall ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualtye, with the doctour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnwriten worde, be not of the churche of god / ergo they be not enſtruct by the holy ghoſt: and conſequently knowe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worde of god. wherfore of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gruence &amp; reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:5102:44"/>
y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; by theyr own reſon, they muſt bylene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, whan we ſay vnto them, this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worde of god, &amp; not we them. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be none of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche approueth ſaynt Paule in the .viij. chapitre to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſaying But if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiryt of Chriſt, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is none of his. The papiſtical ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritualtie, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete of lytell verait, haue not this ſpirit of Chryſt. ergo they be none of his ſorte, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wytneſſe of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Paule. Yea how can they for ſhame be ſo bolde to ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue his ſpiryte, whan they be al vtterly voyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fontes aſeribed &amp; appropriate to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue the ſpirite? Oneles they coulde make good, &amp; fortifie theſe lytle prety ones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre to be the frutes of Chryſtes ſpiryte, as ambicion, pryde, lordlyneſſe, enuy, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce, diſdeyn, preuy &amp; open murdre, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon, tyranny, ſleuthe, eaſe, glotony, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all maner of lechery, brennynge, drownynge, hangyng men i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne gyrdels, ſectes ſciſmes, diuiſion, debate, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſtryfe with Symo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magus &amp; Iudas, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Sodome &amp; Gomorre, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hawkes, horſe, hoores, knaues, theues, &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> naught is,
<pb facs="tcp:5102:44"/>
and whether theſe be the knowen &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt fruites of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtycall kyngdome, the heed, father, &amp; god wherof is Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt of Rome / &amp; his atturney the great god of Cateway, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of vnwritten ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritees / I reporte me to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. And now ye ſe what our vnwriten eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſtes haue won by their owne tale, &amp; to what point &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion they be brought by their vndouted veritees: Forſoth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſure whiche is the worde of god, nor yet be none of his churche / &amp; that for by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be not endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſpiryt, as their fruytes do well declare. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very entent, purpoſe, &amp; pollicy of the authours of the forſayd vnwritten worde was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doutedly, herafter whan they ſhuld haue ſene tyme conuenyent / to haue denyed all holy ſcripture writen, bothe tholde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; the newe to be the worde of god. This is in no wyſe to be doubted. And of this dyuelliſſhe drifte &amp; purpoſe, they put forth this queſtyon to the blynde people, ſayeng. Howe know ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the byble which ye haue dayly in your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and whiche ye rede, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worde of god, but by vs?
<pb facs="tcp:5102:45"/>
Or els to what other entent ſhulde they mone ſuch queſtyons, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they mynded purpoſely to bring me in wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hope &amp; doute of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyng wherin they neuer douted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Oh good lorde, why doeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuffre theſe wretches thyne enemyes ſo longe to reygne, to rule, to deuoure, to murdre, to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e &amp; kyll bothe the body and ſoule of thy poore creatures? Diſcende good lorde diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende, &amp; reuenge the bloode of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> innocent, with the ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drous blaſphemy of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name. Thou haſt here proued vnto the (good chriſten reder) that the byſſhoppe of Rome, otherwyſe vniuſtly called pope, may erre / &amp; howe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the meanes of that ſame foule monſtre &amp; bloodſupper, and by his clientes, this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hath ben greuouſly vexed, troubled, pylled, pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſhorne, ſhauen &amp; ſcraped euen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harde bones and mary: and not onely this realme, but other alſo / the heedes &amp; rulers wherof as before is declared, haue ben of the ſame gargle faced Antichriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his miniſters, ſhamfully handled, vexed, impriſoned &amp; depoſed. And this hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out thautorite either of godd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lawe
<pb facs="tcp:5102:45"/>
or mans, by very power &amp; tyrannye, hym ſelfe beyng but a ſubiect, and of no power without his owne dyoceſe / whiche ought to extende no further than the dyoceſe of the next byſſhop. It is proued alſo by the authorite of ſcripture, that all men ought to be obedyent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngꝭ power, of what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycion or ſtate ſo euer they be / and that vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payne of euerlaſtyng fyre. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I haue annexed that the worde of god writen is ſuffycient to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluacion of our ſoules / &amp; that the vnwriten worde is but a dreame &amp; fantaſye. And nowe prepare thyſelfe to the lyfe of Gregory the ſeuenth ſomtyme byſſhop of Rome / of al tyrantes monſters, &amp; vnfaythful mamalukes that euer was the moſte: wherin thou ſhalt ſe ſuche miſchefe, abhomynacion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eteſtaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, execrable maners, pride, tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, craft, ſubtyltie, ambytion, ſymony, poyſonyng, necromancy, ſettyng vp, puttyng downe, preuenting &amp; ſupplantyng as hath neuer ben ſene in no one mans lyfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer was written or redde. And that not of Gregory alone, but of many other mo ſuche mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters byſſhops of Rome, contayned in the
<pb facs="tcp:5102:46"/>
ſame lyfe of his. Finally (moſt gentle and indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reder) by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme that thou haſt peruſed it / I dare be bolde to affirme that thou woldeſt for no good worldly but that thou haddeſt ſene it. And if thou fynde not my wordes true blame me hereafter, as it ſhall ſeme good vnto the. And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that thou mayſt gyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more credence to the truthe of the hiſtory, thou ſhalt vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was written in latyne (as I tolde the before) by one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt famous and vertuous cardynals that than lyued called Beno. Thou doeſt luſt &amp; longe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture to ſe it / be of good comforte, for with all the ſpede that may be poſſyble, it ſhall be imprinted. And thus in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane whyle fare as well as I wolde my ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>¶ The fawtes in the pryntynge.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Folio. 2. pagina. 2. linea. 21. endued. rede enduced.</item>
               <item>Folio. 7. pagina prima. linea. 24. vertue. rede / vertitie.</item>
               <item>Folio. 9. pagina. 2. linea 20. it with. rede / it of with.</item>
               <item>Folio. 15. pagina. 2. linea. 17. mere. rede / were.</item>
               <item>Folio. 30. pagina. 2. linea. 10. more. rede. mere.</item>
               <item>Folio. 34. pagina prima-linea. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. rede / proues.</item>
               <item>Folio. 36. pagina. 2. linea ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>da. not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. rede / non ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted by wynkyn de worde / for Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Byddell, otherwyſe Saliſbury.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
